Guide to the JoAnn Evansgardner and Gerald H.F. Gardner Papers, 1965-1991 AIS.2001.09
ULS Archives & Special Collections
JoAnn Evansgardner and Gerald H.F. Gardner Papers
1965-1991
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Gardner, G. H. F.
Evansgardner, JoAnn
AIS.2001.09
46.25 Linear Feet (37 boxes)
The Feminist Collection of JoAnn Evansgardner and Gerald H.F. Gardner, 1966-1988, includes records of the National Organization for Women at national, regional, and local Pittsburgh levels. It also contains research and legal proceedings relating to feminist issues such as discrimination by sex in education, employment, healthcare, sports, and politics. This information is provided through minutes, correspondence, court case files, and publications.
Biography
JoAnn Evansgardner and Gerald Gardner have long been active participants in the Civil Rights Movement, joining the NAACP in 1963 and NOW in 1968. JoAnn, born in 1925, spent much of her childhood in the Hazelwood neighborhood of Pittsburgh, but left the city for North Carolina during World War II. After driving vehicles for military officers and trucks for the 2nd Army, she returned to Pittsburgh in 1945 and worked at Mellon Institute on research projects for Union Carbide & Co. Supported by the Institute, JoAnn was able to attend classes at the University of Pittsburgh. She also met and married physicist Gerald Gardner during this time and changed her name from Evans to Evansgardner. After earning her pre-med degree in 1950, Evansgardner lived with Gardner, a native of Ireland, in Dublin for five years before again returning to the University of Pittsburgh to pursue a PhD. in physiological psychology. Evansgardner went on to teach at Carnegie Mellon from 1964 -1966 and give lectures at other institutions, while Gardner worked a chief scientist at Gulf Oil.
Scope and Content Notes
Evansgardner and Gardner joined the National Organization for Women (NOW) in 1968 and were active at the local, state, and national levels throughout the 1970s and 1980s. Evansgardner served on the National Board of NOW and as the Eastern Regional Co-Director, while Gardner served as Director and Treasurer of the First Pittsburgh Chapter. They initiated a lawsuit against the Pittsburgh Press newspaper to ban sex discrimination in want ads, worked for the passage of the Equal Rights Amendment, and helped various other complainants with cases regarding sex and race discrimination. In addition to NOW, Evansgardner and Gardner have been involved with many other feminist, anti-racist, and political activist groups, including the feminist press KNOW, Inc., ACLU, NAACP, Women's Political Caucus, Professional Women's Caucus, International Women's Year, National Women's Conference, and various reproductive rights groups.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of JoAnn Evansgardner and Gerald H.F. Gardner on January 29, 2002.
Previous Citation
JoAnn Evansgardner and Gerald H.F. Gardner Papers, 1965-1991, AIS.2001.09, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Related Material
Additional materials at the Archives Service Center relating to feminism include:
Gerald Blum Papers, 1971-2003, AIS.2005.14, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Marjorie and J. Warren Matson Papers, 1942-1980, AIS.1984.17, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Separated Material
Two folders containing oversize posters have been placed with the oversize materials.
Women; Equal rights amendments -- United States; Women's studies; Women -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Women -- Legal status, laws, etc. -- United States; Women's rights -- United States; Feminism -- United States; Feminists -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Pittsburgh (Pa.) -- Politics and government; Social action; Personal papers; Gardner, G. H. F.; Evansgardner, JoAnn; National Organization for Women. Pennsylvania Chapter; National Organization for Women. Pittsburgh Chapter; National Organization for Women
- National NOW, I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  In response to the failure of the Equal Employment Opportunity Commission to implement Title VII of the Civil Rights Act, which would prohibit employment discrimination based on race, color, religion, sex, or national origin, NOW was established on June 30, 1966 in Washington, D.C., by women attending the Third National Conference of the Commission on the Status of Women. Since its formation, NOW has strived to eliminate discrimination and harassment in the workplace, schools, the justice system, and all other sectors of society; to secure abortion, birth control and reproductive rights for all women; to end all forms of violence against women; to eradicate racism, sexism and homophobia; and to promote equality and justice in our society. Evansgardner served as the Eastern Regional Director of NOW and organized the Eastern Regional Conference in Pittsburgh in 1973.
  Note - Series I. contains organizational records of National NOW. If the researcher is looking for specific issues in which NOW was involved, they may be found in Series II., III., or VII.
  - NOW Statement of Purpose, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Chapter Bylaws, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - National Bylaws, 1970; 1972 (Box 1, Folder 03-04)
  - Bylaw changes, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - National Bylaws, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Policy Manual Updates, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - State Coordinator Plans, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - State Structure Guidelines, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Examples of State Organizing, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - NOW Chapter Kit, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - NOW Chapter Handbook, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Guidelines for Chapter Development, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Eastern Region Packet, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Administrative Manual for Local Chapters, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - NOW Legislative Program, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - NOW Legal Defense Fund, 1971-1974; 1976 (Box 1, Folder 17-18)
  - Public Relations Kit, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Letter Ideas about Running NOW, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Conference Planning, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Phone Bank Manual, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Newsletter Planning and Funding, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Insurance for NOW Members, 1974; 1982 (Box 1, Folder 24-25)
  - Treasurer's Guide, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Financial Development Kit, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - How to Keep a Chapter Budget, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - NOW Reimbursement of Members, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Archives Donation, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - National Application, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Questionnaire, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Membership Processing, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Telephone Network, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - NOW Membership Forms and Lists of Members, 1970-1973 (Box 1, Folder 35-39)
  - NOW Membership Forms and Lists of Members, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 01-03)
  - Questman Mailing List, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Eastern Regional NOW Mailing List, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - NOW Chronology, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - NOW and U.S. Department of Labor, 1969-1972 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Legal Reports, 1970-1975 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Resolutions and Policy Decisions, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Position Papers, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Quarterly Status Reports, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - NOW Improvements, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Legal Defense and Education Fund Annual Report, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - NOW Accomplishments, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Resolutions, 1975, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - U.S. Department of Treasury Harassment Report, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Position Papers, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Implementation Committee Report, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Reports on Twenty Years of Feminism, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Minority Women Report, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Wilma Scott Heide, 1971-1973 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - NOW Correspondence (Box 2, Folder 22-26)
  - Chair-One and President, 1972-1974 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Chapter Presidents, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - National Memos, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 29-30)
  - National and Pittsburgh, NOW, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Evansgardner as Eastern Regional Director, 1973-1975 (Box 2, Folder 32-35)
  - Eastern State Coordinators, 1973-1975 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Eastern State Coordinators, 1973-1975 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous National NOW, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Forms and Press Releases, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Minority committee's Press Release, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Memos, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Public Information Office, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Minutes from Chapter Meetings, 1969-1970 (Box 3, Folder 08-10)
  - Legislative Office, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Education Taskforce, 1972-1973 (Box 3, Folder 12-13)
  - Task Force on Minority and Women's Rights, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Guidelines and Policies for various NOW taskforces, 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Employment Taskforce, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Compliance Taskforce, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Labor Taskforce, 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Taskforce Summaries, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Taskforce Mailings, 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - National NOW Convention, 1970; 1973 (Box 3, Folder 21-23)
  - National NOW Convention, Houston, TX, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 01-02)
  - NOW Board of Directors Orientation Convention, Chicago, IL, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - National NOW Convention, Philadelphia, PA, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 04-05)
  - NOW Constitutional Convention, 1975-1976 (Box 4, Folder 06-07)
  - National Convention, 1977-1985 (Box 4, Folder 08-21)
  - National Convention, 1986-1987; 1972 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - NOW Eastern Regional Conference, 1972-1973 (Box 5, Folder 02-04)
  - Planning the Conference, undated (Box 5, Folder 05-06)
  - Information and Tasks, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Press Kit, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Press Releases, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Attendee Packet, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Advertising Schedules and Slides, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Issues, undated (Box 5, Folder 12-13)
  - Resolutions, undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Reports, undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Items Auctioned, undated (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Eastern Regional Conference Meeting, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Eastern Regional Convention, Atlantic City, NJ, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 18-19)
  - Western Regional Conventions, 1970s (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Southern Regional Conventions, Atlanta, GA, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Midwestern Regional Convention, 1973-1974 (Box 5, Folder 22-23)
  - Texas Democratic Convention and NOW, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - South Carolina Regional Convention, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Executive Committee Memos and Minutes, 1972-1973 (Box 5, Folder 26-27)
  - List of Board Members, 1984-1985; 1988 (Box 5, Folder 28-29)
  - Board of Officers, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - National Board Meetings Agendas, Minutes, and Memos, 1973-1974 (Box 6, Folder 01-08)
  - State Coordinators Meeting, Providence, RI, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Eastern Regional State Coordinators Meeting, New York, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - National Advisory Committee, 1974-1975 (Box 6, Folder 11-12)
  - Nominating Committee, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Finance Committee, 1970-1973 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Employment Committee, 1972; 1970 (Box 6, Folder 15-16)
  - Compliance Committee, 1971-1973 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Committee on Minority Women, 1979-1980 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Nurse's Organization, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Newsclippings, 1969-1979 (Box 6, Folder 20-21)
  - NOW Causes, 1975-1977 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Legal Defense and Education Fund Packets, 1986-1988 (Box 6, Folder 23-24)
  - Recruiting Pamphlet, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Volunteerism Pamphlet, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Civil Rights Restoration Act, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Taft-Hartley Act, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Equal Rights Amendment Packets, 1980-1984 (Box 6, Folder 29-31)
  - Feminist Primer, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - Lesbian Rights Kit, 1981-1982 (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - Campus Campaign Packet, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - NOW Year in Review and NOW Launches 3rd Decade, 1985-1987 (Box 6, Folder 35)
  - Women's Media Campaign Handbook, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - Voting Procedures for National NOW, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - Elections Committee, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 38)
  - Midwest Questionnaires for Candidates, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 39)
  - Majority Caucus for Electing Board Members, 1974-1975 (Box 6, Folder 40)
  - Election Campaign, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 41)
  - Florida Elections, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 42)
  - Strike Day, August 26, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Volunteerism Workshop, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Activist Information Day, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Walk-a-thon, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - NOW-AID, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 05-07)
  - Racism Workshop, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - University of Houston's Day of Workshops, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Treasurer's Reports and Bank Statements, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - National Budget, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 11-12)
  - Budget Reports, 1973-1974 (Box 7, Folder 13-14)
  - Fund-Raising, 1972-1976 (Box 7, Folder 15-17)
- Pennsylvania NOW, II.
  Formed in 1971 and incorporated in 1972, Pennsylvania NOW grew out of a need for communication and organization between localized chapters across the state. Many chapters, already in existence, had been working on such issues as girls' participation in sports, elimination of sexism and racism in children's books, equal access to educational institutions, and affordable day care facilities. Although these efforts were often successful, certain issues – particularly the passage of the Equal Rights Amendment in Pennsylvania – required the widespread coordination afforded by a state chapter. Pennsylvania NOW also provided isolated individuals without local chapters a way of getting involved in the organization. This series is made up of materials relating to the business of Pennsylvania NOW as well as information about its various activities. It also contains appointment books, calendars, and notebooks, which were used to keep track of the many events Evansgardner and Gardner planned and attended. One notebook also includes brief personal accounts of sexism collected from other individuals.
  - Organization Information, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Bylaws, 1973-1979 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Membership and Chapter Lists, 1973-1979 (Box 7, Folder 22-23)
  - Membership Questionnaire, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence, 1973-1979 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Issues, 1973-1979 (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - Press Releases, 1973-1979 (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - Finances, 1973-1975 (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - State Structure Planning Meeting, 1972 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - State Steering Committee, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Meetings and Committees, 1974-1979 (Box 8, Folder 03-08)
  - Political Research Committee, 1977 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - NOW-AID, 1976 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Taskforces, 1973-1979 (Box 8, Folder 11-12)
  - Education Workshop, 1977 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Pennsylvania NOW Convention, 1973-1974 (Box 8, Folder 14-16)
  - Pennsylvania Feminism Conference, Pittsburgh, PA, 1976 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Pennsylvania NOW Convention, 1977-1979 (Box 8, Folder 18-20)
  - Meetings and Issues, 1973-1979 (Box 8, Folder 21-22)
  - Council Meeting, 1976 (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Lawrenceville/Butler County NOW, undated (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Newsletters, 1972-1973 (Box 8, Folder 25-26)
  - PA NOW Mail, 1972-1973 (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - Note/Record Books, Accounts of Sexism, 1972-1973 (Box 8, Folder 28-29)
  - Appointment Reminders, 1970-1972 (Box 8, Folder 30)
  - Notebook, 1976 (Box 8, Folder 31)
  - Notebook/Calendar, undated (Box 8, Folder 32)
  - Organizer, undated (Box 8, Folder 33)
  - Appointment Books, 1978-1979 (Box 8, Folder 34)
  - Bumper Stickers (Box 8, Folder 35)
  - Appointment Books (Box 9, Folder 01-16)
- Pittsburgh Area NOW Chapters, III.
  Pittsburgh was home to many chapters of NOW, most of them associated with individual neighborhoods, such as Squirrel Hill NOW and South Hills NOW. First Pittsburgh NOW, founded by Wilma Scott Heide and chartered in 1967, was the third chapter of NOW founded in the United States. Gardner was very active in First Pittsburgh NOW, serving as Director and as Treasurer. Included in this series are bylaws, meeting minutes, recruitment ideas, address cards, and publications.
  - Sample By-Laws, 1972 (Box 9, Folder 17-18)
  - Notes and Press Releases, 1972 (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Press Kit, 1974 (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Newsclippings, 1966-1969 (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Issues, 1973-1979 (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Various Meetings and Minutes, 1968-1979 (Box 9, Folder 23-24)
  - Board Meeting Minutes, 1973 (Box 10, Folder 01-03)
  - Executive Board, 1971 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Elections, 1969-1975 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Recruitment Ideas, 1975 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Forms, 1973 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Applications, 1973 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Mailing Lists, 1975 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Budget Forms, 1972 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Budgets, 1973 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Treasurer's Reports, 1975 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Budget, 1975-1976 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Address Cards, undated (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Various Pittsburgh NOW Newsletters, 1975-1976 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - First Pittsburgh Chapter News, 1977-1978 (Box 11, Folder 02-03)
  - Campus NOW- University of Pittsburgh, undated (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous Pittsburgh NOW Newsletters and Memos, 1975-1979 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous Newsletters from Chapters in Other Cities, 1971-1989 (Box 11, Folder 6)
- KNOW, Inc., IV.
  Phyllis Wetherby, JoAnn Evansgardner, and Gerry Gardner started a feminist press, KNOW, Inc., under the slogan, "Freedom of the press belongs to those who own the press." KNOW published the first articles and reprints for a burgeoning women's studies movement in 1969. This series includes bylaws, memos, correspondence, finances, reports, and other information on KNOW, 1969-1978, arranged by subject.
  - Bylaws and Organizational Information, 1969-1972 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Board Meetings, 1971-1977 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Finances, 1972-1976 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - KNOW News Service, 1970-1973 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - KNOW News, 1975-1977 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Order Catalogs and Mailing Addresses, 1970-1977 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Articles to be Published, 1969-1977 (Box 11, Folder 13-14)
  - Correspondence, 1971-1977 (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Media Relations, 1975-1978 (Box 11, Folder 16)
- Reproductive Rights and Health Care Topics, V.
  Much of this material relates to NOW's support of the right to safe, legal abortion and includes pamphlets collected from many Pro-Choice and Pro-Life organizations, as well as legislative material and articles on the subject. In addition to abortion rights, NOW was also concerned with all aspects of women's reproductive health, including access to factual information about contraceptive options and sexually transmitted diseases, prenatal care, child care, nutrition, and many other topics. This series includes articles, memos, correspondence, and reports about women's health care at local and national levels, 1973-1974. All records are arranged by subject.
  - Abortion Survey Data, 1970 (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - Child Birth Conference, 1973 (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - Planned Parenthood, 1973-1974 (Box 11, Folder 19-20)
  - Abortion Statistics, 1974 (Box 11, Folder 21)
  - Abortion Biography, 1974 (Box 11, Folder 22)
  - R.C. Tactics, 1975 (Box 11, Folder 23)
  - Abortion Pamphlets, 1974-1975 (Box 11, Folder 24)
  - Family Planning, 1977 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Abortion Arguments, 1970 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Abortion Opposition, 1979 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - National NOW Press Kit, 1974 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Abortion Rights and Legislation Kit, 1975 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Right to Choose Kit, 1978 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Reproductive Rights Resources Kits, 1979-1983 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Reproductive Freedom: Your Right Workshop, 1986 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence between NOW Chapters about Abortion, 1975 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Life Under New Abortion Laws, 1972-1975 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Abortion Newsclippings, 1973 (Box 12, Folder 11-12)
  - Pro-Choice Clippings, 1973-1975 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Pro-Life Clippings, 1975-1976 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Alternatives to Abortion, 1975-1976 (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Articles and Newsletters on Abortion, 1975-1977 (Box 12, Folder 16-17)
  - Memos and Articles on Abortion Rights and Procedures, 1977-1978 (Box 12, Folder 18-19)
  - Pro-Life Lobbyists, 1978 (Box 12, Folder 20)
  - Choice Organizations, 1969-1970 (Box 12, Folder 21)
  - Abortion Justice Associations, 1975 (Box 12, Folder 22)
  - Abortion Rights Association, 1975 (Box 12, Folder 23)
  - Association for the Study of Abortion, 1968-1971 (Box 12, Folder 24)
  - Catholics for Free Choice, 1974 (Box 12, Folder 25)
  - Catholic Newspaper Clippings, 1975 (Box 12, Folder 26)
  - Clergy Committee, 1970 (Box 12, Folder 27)
  - Committee for Human Life, 1970 (Box 12, Folder 28)
  - Day of Outrage, 1975 (Box 12, Folder 29)
  - National Abortion Rights Action League, 1975 (Box 13, Folder 01-03)
  - Other Abortion Organizations, 1970-1971 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Pennsylvania Abortion Rights Association, 1971 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Religious Coalition on Abortion Rights, 1975 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - SW PA Coalition, 1974 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Women's National Abortion Action Coalition, 1971-1972 (Box 13, Folder 08-09)
  - Abortion Rights Petitions, 1970-1975 (Box 13, Folder 10-11)
  - Abortion Politics Mailings, 1975 (Box 13, Folder 12-13)
  - Abortion Politics Correspondence, 1975 (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Abortion Politics Workshop, 1975 (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - Abortion Laws, 1969-1971 (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - Use Your Voice: Congressional Districts Views on Abortion, 1975 (Box 13, Folder 17)
  - Pro-Life Legislation, 1973-1974 (Box 13, Folder 18)
  - U.S. Abortion Bill, 1975 (Box 13, Folder 19)
  - Caligiuri Resolutions, 1978 (Box 13, Folder 20)
  - House Bill 71, 1978 (Box 13, Folder 21)
  - Senate Bills Correspondence, 1979 (Box 13, Folder 22)
  - Women's Centers, 1974 (Box 13, Folder 23)
  - Medical Care, 1973 (Box 13, Folder 24)
  - Self Help Centers, 1973 (Box 13, Folder 25)
  - Involuntary Commitment, 1974 (Box 13, Folder 26)
- Education Topics, VI.
  Many universities first began offering Women's Studies programs and classes in the late 1960's and early 1970's. Evansgardner collected brochures and professors' notes from these early attempts. Although most university programs were open to women by this time, female students and faculty were still discriminated against and underrepresented in many disciplines. This series documents this period in women's history through pamphlets on women in law schools, statistics on the number of female students graduating from particular programs, and educational lawsuits. Lawsuits include Braden vs. the University of Pittsburgh, in which a group of women accused the university of discriminating against and underpaying female faculty, failing to support their research, and providing inadequate daycare for working mothers. The second half of the series contains information on Title IX, which passed in 1972 and requires gender equity to boys and girls in all educational programs that receive federal funding, including school sports teams. The integration of women into school sports generated many questions and controversies, and NOW formed a Sports Committee to address problems. This series also includes a section on daycare and other child care facilities.
  - Program Funding, 1968-1969 (Box 13, Folder 27)
  - List of College Syllabi Compiled by KNOW, 1970 (Box 13, Folder 28)
  - College of Female Studies and Faculty, 1973 (Box 13, Folder 29)
  - Courses on Women, 1970 (Box 13, Folder 30-31)